<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Lessons From Other Worlds</title>
 <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/"/>
 <updated>2019-03-02T15:44:03-05:00</updated>
 <id>https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com</id>
 <author>
   <name>The Writer!</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>The Power by Naomi Alderman</title>
   <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/speculative/2019/02/20/the-power-naomi-alderman.html"/>
   <updated>2019-02-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/speculative/2019/02/20/the-power-naomi-alderman</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/7Lt4a&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=0316547611&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=0316547611&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender discrimination is a hot topic these days. And with good reason; there are plenty of stats (for those willing to see them) of there being a gender pay gap, of women being victimized and generally being treated as a lesser part of society. On top of that, there is simply an underlying systemic prejudice that everyone seems to have that women are incapable of (or need help with) fulfilling roles that are traditionally held by men. “Oh, she must have known someone really well to get there…” is probably the tamest thing people say in this type of situation, and it gets MUCH worse from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I recently welcomed our daughter into the world, after two sons. When we found out we were most likely going to have a daughter, I have to admit that, as a father, I was scared. I was scared in a way I had not been with our boys. A lot of it came from my knowledge of the aforementioned prejudice that our society has towards women, but on top of that, there was a deep-seated concern that I needed to be the kind of man that would show her what she should expect other men to be like. I wanted to teach her that she should expect equal respect and dignity, and the exact same treatment as any man around her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, as parents, we do the best we can, and I will take this day by day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The novel I am discussing today, &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/7Lt4a&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Naomi Alderman, does not necessarily help with finding an answer to gender discrimination issues. It does, however, like the best speculative fiction, use a scenario that is just slightly off from the real world to shine a light of different perspective on issues we face every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a touch of Margaret Atwood’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/AIVks&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Handmaid’s Tale&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in this story, and with good reason. As Alderman mentions in an interview,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“I’d been to an Orthodox Jewish primary school where every morning the boys said, ‘Thank you God for not making me a woman.’ If you put that together with &lt;em&gt;The Handmaid’s Tale&lt;/em&gt; in your head, something will eventually go fizz! Boom!”&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, Atwood and Alderman worked together on this novel through the Rolex mentorship program; in fact, Atwood even suggested a certain location for some scenes which have a massive impact on the narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main portion of the story is framed by a narrative involving a male writer, Neil Adam Armon, and his female editor, named Naomi(!). More than anything else in the book, this framework really sets the tone for how the story is going to play out. The gender dynamic between these two characters is extremely poignant, bringing to mind many of the ways men undermine women in our own society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the novel, it is shown that young women (between their teenage years and into their thirties) have suddenly gained the ability to generate and shoot electricity from their fingertips. This “power” comes from a new organ that has grown over their collarbones that they name the skein, due to the way it looks like a roll of thread. Not much explanation is given as to how this ability came to be, but many, many theories are presented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main narrative is broken down into chapters that each involve one of several characters: Allie, a teenage girl living with foster parents; Roxy, the daughter of a London mob boss; Margot, a politician in the US; Jocelyn, Margot’s teenage daughter; Tatiana, the First Lady of a European nation; and the only primary male character, Olatunde Edo, a journalist. This narrative method is one of the keys to the effectiveness of this novel, as it gives you over-the-shoulder insight into the thoughts and impressions of characters at the forefront of the changes society is facing due to this global event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human element does not end there. None of the aforementioned characters are good, or bad… They are just people, trying to work with the hand they have been dealt. The results are, to put it mildly, fascinating. By no means is any of this presented as a utopia; throughout the world, there are women shown who fight back against the oppression they have suffered for centuries; others do their best to figure out how to adjust to this change to a new global power dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Power&lt;/em&gt; provides an absolutely fascinating look at what could happen if the entire population of women in the world suddenly gains complete and fully effective agency. That is perhaps its most intriguing and powerful trait, and is something that hit the right note with me as the new father of a daughter!`&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this review, please consider clicking on the Amazon links above to support this site. It really helps with book purchasing costs and with the continued development of the site. Thanks for your support!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/books/bookreviews/9480151/Margaret-Atwood-mentors-Naomi-Alderman.html&quot;&gt;“Margaret Atwood Mentors Naomi Alderman”&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Telegraph&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Changeling by Victor LaValle</title>
   <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/fantasy/horror/2019/02/06/the-changeling-victor-lavalle.html"/>
   <updated>2019-02-06T12:58:10-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/fantasy/horror/2019/02/06/the-changeling-victor-lavalle</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/292YcbB&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=0812995945&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=0812995945&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet infiltrates every part of our lives nowadays, particularly here in the developed world. Smartphones with cameras and always-on internet access have become so ubiquitous that entire business categories have sprung up to take advantage of this new communication method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when this creeping entity, that has its tentacles in all of our homes and lives, suddenly turns against us? As a father of three kids, one of my greatest concerns is being able to protect my children from the various harms that society could inflict on them. There are definitely things that I can control, but even within reality, there are things I have no control over. But what if the threat ends up having ties to the supernatural?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of Lovecraftian sensibility in Victor LaValle’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/292YcbB&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Changeling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is no surprise. He did, after all, pen the story &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/XcvdJA&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Ballad of Black Tom&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which is a retelling of H.P. Lovecraft’s tale &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/g9MBF7P&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Horror at Red Hook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. There is a palpable sense of creeping horror as you continue pacing through this story, and it never quite leaves you once you are done reading the last word and have gone back to your life. At least, that’s what happened to me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It starts off innocently and happily enough. The first portion of the book details the childhood and early adulthood of the protagonist, named Apollo. The story takes a darker turn around a third of the way in, and without giving away any spoilers (given the title), we can say it has a lot to do with kidnapped children. In addition to the darker aspects, the plot contains some magical elements in the latter part of the story, and at first, I had a hard time reconciling these with the rest of the book taking place in modern society. Although I am intimately familiar with fantastical fiction, something about the magic didn’t quite click.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This all changed when my perception of the book was corrected. I had been trying to think of this as an urban fantasy, which it is most definitely not. The answer came from the discussion of fairy tales that one of the characters has with Apollo, about two-thirds of the way into the book. Fairy tales are meant to be a society’s response to fears and feelings that they don’t understand. Historically, they were often very dark and foreboding (think Grimm’s tales), and were used as a way to put into words those threats you couldn’t quite put your finger on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was the answer; &lt;em&gt;The Changeling&lt;/em&gt; is a fairy tale about parenthood in the modern age. When you read it like that, everything falls into place. The aspects of the story that seemed cliche before, now make sense and help build the story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve been following along, here we have a book that combines a dash of Lovecraft with a large helping of fairy tale sensibilities and deals with parenting in modern society. A winning combination, without a doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first story that I had read from Victor LaValle, and I have since read &lt;em&gt;The Ballad of Black Tom&lt;/em&gt;, and am still impressed with his ability to use words to build an image in your mind. I am truly looking forward to seeing what else he can pull out of his considerable imagination!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this review, please consider clicking on the Amazon links above to support this site. It really helps with book purchasing costs and with the continued development of the site. Thanks for your support!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dune by Frank Herbert</title>
   <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/science-fiction/2019/01/23/dune-frank-herbert.html"/>
   <updated>2019-01-23T12:58:10-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/novel/science-fiction/2019/01/23/dune-frank-herbert</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
    &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/vAwq9&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=0441172717&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=0441172717&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What can be said about &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/vAwq9&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; that hasn’t already been said? Since the novel’s release in 1965, it has spawned numerous sequels (written by Frank Herbert himself), a multitude of prequel stories (co-written by Herbert’s son Brian, and Kevin J. Anderson), and film and TV adaptations that, despite their questionable faithfulness to the original material, have gained a massive cult following.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond the material that does exist, an attempt was made in the 1970s by the avant-garde director Alejandro Jodorowsky to make the first film based on &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;. After $2 million of the $9.5 million budget (a massive sum at the time) were spent just in pre-production, with a projected film-length of 14 hours (!), the project failed. David Lynch would later film his version of the novel, releasing it in 1984, to a lot of fan controversy over the changes made to the universe in the film. Denis Villeneuve will also be directing a new version, which as of this post, is in the beginning stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is it about this novel that has been so hard to capture in film? And why does it have such staying power? Can a science fiction novel from the 1960s still be relevant today? For the purposes of this discussion, we will be focusing on the original novel &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;, as this author strongly feels that it can stand on its own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One aspect of &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; that the reader should pick up on immediately is the “inner conversation” that many of the primary characters have with themselves. This makes it seem like there is a constant narrative being provided to the reader, giving insight into the universe that they are now being made a part of. It works reasonably well, once you get used to it, but is likely one of the reasons this novel has been hard to film accurately. After all, how can you visually and aurally present thoughts on the screen, without making it seem contrived?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this novel, there is also a focus on a more “civilized” society trying to control what they consider backward savages. The novel’s namesake planet, Dune (or Arrakis as it is locally called), is the only source of the spice &lt;em&gt;melange&lt;/em&gt;, which is a drug that the entire Galactic Empire depends on. It is needed for faster than light space travel, and has miraculous healing and age-extending properties. However, Arrakis is populated by an old civilization known as the Fremen, who are clearly modeled after Bedouins from our own history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep a watchful eye on spice production, the Galactic Emperor designates one of the great noble Houses to run the spice extraction and export processes. Up to the beginning of the novel, the sinister House Harkonnen has been running the show, but the Emperor, for some reason, decides to give the job to the noble House Atreides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right off the bat, you meet Paul, the heir to House Atreides, and the protagonist of this story. He is quite disappointed with having to leave his home and being relegated to a backward planet. Without giving away too much, future events will definitely make him see his experience differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you delve further into the story, you begin to experience an intricately developed universe, with a deep-rooted belief system surrounding the spice and the sandworms that rule the deserts of Arrakis. Using this religion, Paul is able to get the aid of the Fremen for his mission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have not read &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt; as of yet, what have you been doing?! But on a serious note, if you are a fan of science-fiction or fantasy in any capacity, you must read &lt;em&gt;Dune.&lt;/em&gt; Many later novels by new authors have been inspired by Frank Herbert’s work, but there is something about the story, atmosphere, and universe that Herbert created that stands the test of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this review, please consider clicking on the Amazon links above to support this site. It really helps with book purchasing costs and with the continued development of the site. Thanks for your support!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Mistborn Trilogy by Brandon Sanderson</title>
   <link href="https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/series/fantasy/2019/01/09/mistborn-trilogy-brandon-sanderson.html"/>
   <updated>2019-01-09T12:58:10-05:00</updated>
   <id>https://lessonsfromotherworlds.com/review/series/fantasy/2019/01/09/mistborn-trilogy-brandon-sanderson</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;div class=&quot;row&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/uePpPmr&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=B002GYI9C4&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=B002GYI9C4&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt;
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/6NBMZr&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=0765356139&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=0765356139&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;column&quot;&gt; 
        &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://geni.us/aO0W&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; src=&quot;//ws-na.amazon-adsystem.com/widgets/q?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;MarketPlace=CA&amp;amp;ASIN=0765356147&amp;amp;ServiceVersion=20070822&amp;amp;ID=AsinImage&amp;amp;WS=1&amp;amp;Format=_SL250_&amp;amp;tag=twocanpub-20&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;//ir-ca.amazon-adsystem.com/e/ir?t=twocanpub-20&amp;amp;l=am2&amp;amp;o=15&amp;amp;a=0765356147&quot; width=&quot;1&quot; height=&quot;1&quot; border=&quot;0&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; style=&quot;border:none !important; margin:0px !important;&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first heard about Brandon Sanderson, it was a short while before he had been selected to complete &lt;em&gt;The Wheel of Time&lt;/em&gt; series after the untimely death of the original author, Robert Jordan. I had heard about the Mistborn series, but then decided to read his novel &lt;a href=&quot;https://geni.us/ZakIWO&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elantris&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; first, to get an idea of his style (review upcoming).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After (spoiler alert) thoroughly enjoying &lt;em&gt;Elantris&lt;/em&gt;, I was STOKED to get into the Mistborn series, which at the time only had the first two books released. The premise seemed interesting; a dystopian medieval world where a prophesied hero was defeated and the “Dark Lord” won? A heist plan a la &lt;em&gt;Ocean’s Eleven&lt;/em&gt; to steal a valuable treasure from the aforementioned Dark Lord? SIGN ME UP!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of the above information is spoilers, by the way. This is simply the premise of the first book, and the story is developed on top of that quite heavily through the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more interesting aspects of Sanderson’s stories has always been the well-designed magic systems, something he has come to be known for. In this world, certain individuals have developed a mutation which gives them heightened abilities (increased strength, speed, senses, etc) when they ingest certain kinds of metal flakes. Different metals give different abilities. Most of the time, these individuals can only gain effects from one particular metal, and are called Mistings. Sometimes, however, you get Mistborn, who are people that can gain enhancements from a full array of metals, and can in fact combine effects by taking metal “cocktails.” Without revealing too much, Mistborn do appear in these novels, and boy, do they ever steal the show! They are the source of some absolutely incredible fight scenes and acrobatics, the kind of stuff that is usually reserved for superhero movies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mist being referred to in the title is this strange fog that envelops the world at night. There are many legends surrounding it, and it is even thought to be the source of the Mistborn’s powers. Many details on this are revealed later on in the series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A discussion of the Mistborn series would be incomplete without mentioning Sanderson’s Cosmere concept. This is a shared universe where many of the books he has written are somehow connected with an overarching plot and universe, and this is slowly being revealed. When the Mistborn books originally came out, the Cosmere had not been revealed at all as of yet, but when you go back and re-read them, there are definitely little signs sprinkled throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we still wait for all aspects of the Cosmere to be revealed, I recommend that any fan of unique fantasy stories get to a bookstore immediately and read the Mistborn series. This universe is also still being built, as Sanderson is writing a second trilogy (The Wax and Wayne series), set 300 years after this first series, in a Western/industrial setting. Imagine superheroes that manipulate metal in a world with guns! On top of that, he has also announced plans to set a couple of trilogies in this world, which will take place even further in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one negative thing to be said about all this, it’s that sometimes it can feel like too much. The Cosmere is an enormous and detailed place, and keeping track of how things are connected can be overwhelming. But Sanderson does a fair job of keeping his books individually readable, relegating most shared universe reveals to small side scenes that don’t necessarily affect the main plot, with very few exceptions. This makes his books incredibly readable and enjoyable, and we look forward to the next release!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you enjoyed this review, please consider clicking on the Amazon links above to support this site. It really helps with book purchasing costs and with the continued development of the site. Thanks for your support!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
